foreign what's the
what's the
what's the point of the practice
what's the measurable point
what is the successful practice result
in
I mean obviously there are many ways you
can answer this but let's just start
answering it
one way would be
not being bothered as much
mm-hmm and and
how that
how is that practically measured
in terms of insight
that is to talk about
how would you know that you're along the
right lines I mean yeah because what can
happen is people can
on account of practice because they were
inspired to practice
but they were kind of inadvertently
still be addressing the circumstances
avoiding and so on and in the end like
build up a little environment that
nothing bothers them
and then everything is sort of at the
armed land so then they feel like oh
look my practice is succeeding because I
don't suffer as much factually
but over time you do it you know one two
three years you start to be able to
manage things well exactly you become a
bit more hardened and hardened
individual yeah so but so you wouldn't
you wouldn't say that you would you
wouldn't you couldn't use that as a as a
measure of successful practice like
because what inside do you have button
sorry about if your mind moves on
account of the thought of
you dying
yeah okay so how would then
what inside
is required
for a mind to not move on a kind of a
thought of dying what is the culminating
insight there
the suit is often talk about Anita
well what's the inside of that Anita
what the Anita and Duke are coming in
well it's done itself exactly so that is
the measure
the complete cessation well first of the
self-view then your Notions of
personality and conceit
and when that is absent completely gone
without any traces
then yeah you couldn't suffer even if
you wanted
so this is the measure that the less
somebody take things personally the more
they are focusing in the practice could
be but you know you have like
psychotherapeutical methods that teach
you how to not take things personal but
you're taking that personally
so it has to be an actual insight into
another and it's like nuts it's not something
and it's like nuts it's not something
you can stumble upon accidentally that
uh another
um that's where you need the learning
you need the only instrumental you need
practice central strength but yeah it's
a factual irreversible insight to put it
away
and then on each other
it's just so that you can actually
experience the another
so then
what is another
can I am
because it it that is really what makes
the difference it's not
it's not like yeah because I haven't
talked about this before
how you can say okay my mind your mind
won't be bothered by let's say even the
thought of dying
but it's
um more fundamental than just sort of
having become sort of so strong or so
kind of mentally sure that now nothing
bothers you yeah that's a prerequisite
for the inside of um but as the Buddha
said himself in other you know
dispensation at the time they were
teachers that you could factually
establish United perception or
perception whether it means you're
pretty much onboarded by anything
anything inferior to that as a sudas
would say
now he said only in his teaching only
the dispensation of the Buddhas you will
get the uh another part inside
um so yes yeah we're not being bothered
and even this is what they say you know
I don't mind does not get overrun by
things might overwhelms things and so on
so it's a factual strength that is
developed they're obviously without
which you couldn't understand and
feel fully developed the anata but there
is that part of another yeah
so say you have been sense of strange in
the Danish size for guardian of the
sense of keeping the presets slowing
solitude um
um
so okay you're meeting the requirements
let's say that to stop seeing
Pata slash
abandoning it
so
what is that
is like something that would just occur
and then you could interpret it in
hindsight or do you need to know where to look for
or do you need to know where to look for
in order to see it and then start
looking up until you recognize it
well let's start what's the necessary
basis for Renata
seeing Arthur yeah peripheral yeah
so what is up to them let's define that
person it's it's always peripheral you
can't put it in front of you so the
properties are like that the properties
of the sense of self would be
it's not directly visible like
you can't actually with your senses
you can't observe it with your five
senses and you certainly can't just oh
yeah this is myself that I'm just
relating to so it's always ambiguous yes
what else
after the sense of self is the center of
experience yeah but let's not speak
theoretically let's instead like
everybody now has a sense of self to
some degree
I presume so
describe what is it where does it say
that it's it's
um automatic and that's one is actively
seeking to clarify that ambiguous
sense of self it is
um
yeah is it automatically automatic in
the sense that whenever you experience
pain you will automatically want to get
rid of it whenever you experience
pleasure you'll automatically want sure
but we're talking about the sense of
self that linger is always in the
background of it
so regardless of your reactions
do you have the experience of my dead
self's not there no
so it's always just some degree you know
sometimes might feel clear sometimes
might not but that sense of I am sense
of self
Center the center of the experience it's
always there
so but do you see it right now as we
speak do you see your own sense itself
and during the on its own somehow
somewhere Ambiguously just kind of
lingering to have it to have that sense of self
to some degree
so and that's the key there basically
the way to start seeing it is to learn
how to sit on its own degree
not how to make it into an object that I
think it should be of my observation of
my direct attention
and that's the again the Solitude and
the practice of mindfulness as we said
before well as you said yesterday in particular
well as you said yesterday in particular
you know
mindfulness is memory of your present
experience that's what something is
is
nothing complicated about it if you were
to abandon the views of mindfulness
being the concentrating on the present
moment I'm Mindful and I'm here and here
having the memory of the present moment
right here while we speak that's very my
that's where mindfulness is practice of
memory here and now so it's like a a
different way
a different angle let's say like that
of attending to
what is here now in front of me directly
attended so it's not something you can like if I
so it's not something you can like if I
ask you really call a memory or
something just remember something where
would you how would you do that would
you stare at things and feel the
sensations of the body and focus to get
memory no you'll be quite opposite and
focused from what you were focused on
to recall recollect
but it's there
that point of view of memory
whether it's memory of this second while
I'm saying memory memory memory
it's there or it's the memory from 10
years ago
it doesn't matter it's the same point of
view it's the point of view that you can
use to observe the present experience at
the same time you are in the present
experience just indirectly
just indirectly
so it's the background of your current
absorbed attention point of view of your
senses it's the con it's what the mind
is
and that ambiguous sense of self
is kind of here and there neither here
nor there in between the two
if you're off The View
that that sense of self is something you
can think directly
something you can access your sensor
directly something you can attend
observe and see it as anata
you're not seeing the sense of self
you're just chasing the idea that you
have intellectually developed
of it on account of you know reading the
sutures and so on listen to talks the
point is sense itself
is always
behind from where you're looking
but then when you realize
that the range
the range
for like a very word of where you can
look is either directly attended or the
direction of that memory point of view
Sati you realize oh you don't need to
know specifically where the sense itself
is you know that it will have to be
between the two points of view
they're there at the same time
as you see yesterday with this this is
so it's under the memory point of view
where the mind is comes first in a sense
it exists on its own and then the senses
come up no they exist simultaneously but
yeah one is the way of the direct
attention that you can access to the
world the other one is the knowledge of
you with the direct potential that you
connect to the world and that is
something memory it's used
interchangeable in the suitors the
problem is the people when they hear the
memory they have a view of past
implicitly passed but even if it's the
past it's presently recollected
serious okay so I could technically as a
practice instead of only recollecting
the past I could regret what is present
in during just not allow myself to
directly attend it but know it on the
level of memory
like are you seated now
yes and that's memory see the immediate
answer you you don't need to wait I need
to feel my knees
the recognition of that
simultaneously enduring point of view is
there
yeah so it's like two two points of
observance of the same thing
and because they're two neither can be
one in charge Master experience
so with this this is without this this
wouldn't be either way there's no room
for ownership now that's all good and
Wild on theory in theory and that aspect
but so yes practically let's say you
start practicing something correctly in
the Solitude you're recollecting what
you're presently doing instead of
attending to what you're presently doing
so keeping that peripheral point of view
watching what is presently you know
seating breathing whatever memory
breathing that's exactly what it is
memory of current breeding
but not accessing it to the point of
view directly attending the sensations
of it but I've seen it to the indirect
point of view of knowledge of it the
recognition of the of the images of
reading that you're doing basically the
memory that's what Memories so the sense itself
that's what Memories so the sense itself
the Atta
however ambiguous it might be however
fleeting or unclear it might be
it is real as such
as I keep saying
so instead of you trying to see it on
the level of directly attended
experience or myself myself
you need to see it for whatever it is
however it is a vague cloud
sometimes more palpable sometimes not
but the sense of self sense of I am is
their lingering
and you can't go behind it in other
words you can't become the Observer of
it and put it as an object it's always
going to be behind you so how do you
make it then
um not
not perpetually escaping you
well I think this this uh elusivity
is important in terms of seeing it in
its own terms so yeah so first you
realize okay so I cannot not I cannot
make it not elusive it's going to still
lose it so I need to accept ambiguity of
it
as its characteristic
so ambiguity should be enough for me to
recognize it as being there
because everybody recognizes Ambiguously
but then it has the pressure the impulse
the tendency to okay let me clarify it
because the only way I can relate to it
is if it is more defined but it's not
it's an ambiguous phenomenon
it's it's neither here nor there but it
is real as such
so that's why you shouldn't dismiss it
nor should you try to like overly Define
it and you should certainly not mystify
it it's still a phenomenon like any
other thing any other image in the mind
so if you keep trying to directly access
it it's always going to slip through
fingers so how do you then access it without
so how do you then access it without
you know grabbing it so to speak
like you say about memories so there's
all already
by surmounting in a sense that we just
described and recognizing exactly memory
okay so the knowledge of it
the recognition there is an ambiguous
thing that's neither in my senses nor
away from it it's kind of always there
yeah but whatever it is
it has to be in between has to be within
this and this
it has to be between what I'm directly
attending and the knowledge the memory
of what I'm directly attending cannot be
outside of it
Reco like that
Factory on the basis of your currently
enduring a bigger sense of self not just
theoretically frequently enough
frequently enough
and dwell in solitude when you're
collecting it frequently enough and once
you establish that idea that it's fact
based on the the factual ambiguity of
the center self okay so this sense
itself that you know I'm not trying to
Define but I'm not ignoring either has
to be between this and this
and let it endure them when you forget
it we establish it again and again and
again and that's how you basically
uproot approved not the sense of self
immediately but uproot The View that the
sense of self can be outside
of this outside of the experience the
whole outside of the fire audience
whichever we want to Define it you don't
know it cannot be answered if I look
that way or if I look at the memory way
those are the two ends nothing can be
outside of it
so all of the sense of self feels
inaccessible Direction it's always none
of this pertains to it it has to be
within this
cannot be outside of it because all I
have is this and this now can I even
know outside because even the thought
about side of this experience in
external world and so on it's within
this and this
within me directly attending it and
having the memory of it there is no
outside of that
you know that that's all that appears
like what's in front well and a lot more
appears in between
but not outside of it and when I say in
between I don't mean in a third place in
between the two means on the basis of
these two simultaneous things that's
what people describe
like they did mutually there is no first
one which comes like two sticks leaning
on each other equally
so they cannot even standing if you
remove one
to expand a bit on what you mean by
these two directions
um maybe it's useful to use the um
like these two common wrong views for
example of empiricism or idealism the
idea that there is one company
yeah yeah so but that's the point so you
would say the materialism or or that
kind of external point of view
scientific view it's always on the basis
on the attention attention direct
attention and the senses then you could
have solipsism or idealism or all sorts
of variations there will be no no it's
my mentor comes first but no they're
simultaneous to the same extent the
point to the same extent and that's what
it's about in the nutshell with this
this is
without this this wouldn't be that's it
that's the recognition like the other
hand does not destroy these two things
to become another one he just fully
removes any traces of ignorance in
regard to it
but with this this is
and practically again as opposed to
theoretically this this and that and
external world internal what I'm both at
the same time
it's yeah what you're currently
attending to it's like this seated body
Here and Now
and I can think about this seated body
here and now I can have a memory of it
here and now I can't remember what that
here and now was yesterday
but this here now was two days ago maybe
even more and the more that we drove
from and expand my mind from the senses
I can have a memory that would go even
past this life
the point is it's still within the same
two points of view that they're
simultaneously present
so if you
that's all you have by the way that's
all you ever had it's just that there is
a confusion
and all this sort of
um like net of of messy View and what
comes first in one second and everything
else in between so generally that
results into the the weight of the
experience being put on that sense of
self as the owner as that's outside of
this point of view so sense of self can
remember the sense of self can attend
Kansas do both can look in between
is it even that sense of self as
ambiguous as it is it is still in a
recent phenomena that you can have a
memory of
so it's actually an object not of direct
attention but
in its own regard it is really such as a
thing that exists in your mind
so and if so means you are not it yeah
fundamental thing now you can say Okay
results and yourself
he's like well no there is sense of self
you just need to stop putting it first
find that upon which it depends and see
that see two points of view is just
seeing your experience is fundamentally
determined simultaneously by two points
of view at once
one of the memory one of the direct
attention means neither of them can take place as
means neither of them can take place as
the center of Master experience
impossible when there are two there
cannot be one on
because they're equal twos
so then any notion of external any
notion of scientific observation any
views that you have has to be within it
and the notion of solipsist will hold on
foreign has to be within two
but teach somebody and often like when
people ask the Buddha about the
ask the Buddha about the
the sense of self because they heard
that's what he teaches
if they were like really wrong if they
say sorry there is no self I implying
that no self is this self or any other
mystification he would just be silent
but on some other occasions people did
ask him kind of the same question and he
replied but not to the question and I
remember first time long time ago why
why does he give this seemingly
non-reply as a reply to their question of what
as a reply to their question of what
itself what is an actor so he would say
with this this is with the rising of
ignorance
I was like
Super Why would you why would you give
that as an answer to where is my sense
of self and areas well this is why
that's what it is
if you undermine what this this is if
you full understand it there is no side
of it if you fully abandon it yeah
that's how you get the not self that
you're asking about so it's the most
direct answer to what not self is to how
to be developed
now of course you know the Buddha being
the Buddha could describe this with this
this is
uh in many sort of more kind of subtle
details and Pairs and whatever else is
sort of traditionally as you but it's
just describing the aspects and
everything else that depends upon those
with this this is and everything else
that depends is the entire Samsung side
it's the birth age and death in another
in another suit that he doesn't actually
describe it in these 12 factors but from
birth goes into taking up sticks and
stones and killing each other and
harming and everything that happens in
the world in another suit that doesn't
even go to a video
just stops with namurupa vignana
contemplating that purification of the
Mind cessation of the Notions of cell
fundamentally all you need to
contemplate is with this this is under
our level with what with what what is
well with this that I'm directly
attending to my experience as a whole
that is the image of the experience as a
whole there is a memory of it
simultaneously present otherwise you
wouldn't even know experience as a hold
it should attended to as the experience
as a whole that you attended to that's
where it simultaneous one feeds the
other one defines the other
if there are no senses that are
attending in in sort of operating in
their own domain there will be nothing
to have an image of
if there is no image recollection memory
of
the senses and the world that the senses
are in while nothing would be
intelligible you will not be any
conscious being
and that's with this this is that's it
so now anything that happens throughout
the day
you make sure it stays within the
context of with this this is
with this this is
and there was a suit that's when the
Buddha says and he wouldn't go in more
details he would just question amongst
Max do you see with this this has arisen
yes do you see that with this as as a
present condition this has to be yes do
you see that without this this isn't yes
Max that view as pure as it is as
precise as it is if you were to not
maintain it practice it cut with it
further but just sort of venerated would
that result in Liberation or you
wouldn't so monks don't just venerate it
do it keep doing it
and he described that as the cleanest
purest View
because it doesn't have these secondary
definitions it's with this this is
everybody starts with that phrase with
this this is to both present tenses and
then we what and then it goes into the
stands and then descriptions and so on
but the principle remains unchanged
despite what they're sort of you know a
commentary or contemporary
interpretation did somebody would like
to believe
the principle of two simultaneously
present things
it remains whether you're talking about
birth and death or vinyana the principle
of this this is and everything else is
in between and that's where the monk who
practices that rightly
establishes that he he doesn't take I to
be first I my own or forms in the world
or mind or mental objects and says
everything else in between the eye
Consciousness and the feelings that
would rise on account of in all the
other experiences that would in between
this relationship he won't take as his
whereas if you ignore
the principle you will you defaulted
back to your
perversion of the order of putting your
sentence out first or whatever else
whereas if you're not ignorant you
cannot do yeah if you make the effort to
not ignore the order and whatever you're
experiencing on the basis of sense to
strength virtue Solitude you include
in the order with this this is there is
an outside of it it doesn't matter if
it's more on the mental memory side more
on the palpable side doesn't matter so
that we keep saying content doesn't
matter the nature of things matters oh
it's present as such that's all you
matter you know whichever way it feels
you've got to be felt within this and
this no outside of it and when I think
oh there's no outside of it as an
outside of it that's within the enduring
body here and the memory I've been doing
body here
so it's still enclosed within the same
principle the moment you hammer in
whereby you cannot
forget let's say that
that there is no outside of this and
this that's where your roundabout is
gone and and that's it like so you can't you
and and that's it like so you can't you
still continue to operate externally you
you might well still look the same
but your assumption of external to this
and this is now inconceivable because it
is inconceivable conceiving it is seen
within this because you have developed
the perspective of this and this
sufficiently enough to include the
wildest of your careless fantasy
imagination assumption it's still seen
rightly a second within this football
and now if you sustain
invest the effort purify
establish endure that view
more throughout there will be no more
even room for any slightest traces of
conceit to remain
because you know you might have
abandoned the view of the external
entity of me existing independent of
this you still have this like subtler
habits leanings cravings and so on they
kind of imply to that much of the degree
sort of Independence it's still within
but it's a bit but you realize not even
that cannot stand if the principle is
supposedly developed
dam is fulfilled that's what exactly is
the suit is
the dhamma that's it no delay there
and it's the direct most as I said as
the Buddha said the purest thing the
view that if you cultivate it will
can only result in the complete
purification of of your being removal
and cessation of passion greed
a version and delusion because all of
those things reply imply a degree of
that seat self-centeredness some degree of
seat self-centeredness some degree of
uh craving banana that can stand if this
view is absolutely thoroughly hammered
in in and out
could it be correctly said thus
the
removal of atavada is
to
see that
view of patriot
rightly as you described and then
it's it's almost then you be you don't
need the view anymore you can't have
that even that pure view anymore to it
to if even that concedes on that level
as you described is removed because you
would be it in the sense that partition
or something is what you are yes yes
sure sure is what you are yeah
conceived left well even that views is
now redundant he doesn't need to
recollect and re-establish that view
because there's nothing perverting it so
yeah he goes beyond the view he is it
there isn't it like the noble level path
I think imagine
and then for another hand he gets that
like two more factors yeah that's right
and one of them is uh like gone beyond
the view
yeah Liberation and knowledge and vision
of Liberation so yeah something like
that yeah and when that was described it
was like he has gone beyond the view
which means even the the right to you
the right it's gone
he doesn't have it anymore because he
has no wrong reference in regard to it
anymore to define it
whereas even one who would see that kind
of still has the other reference to that
extent yeah yeah yeah so he still needs
to lean and work and cultivate onto the
side of the right but it can never
really fall back onto the other
reference well he can fall back up to
the you know to the factors that he has
abandoned he can't fall back beyond that
so tupana can abandon his training and
become careless and not not not invest
more effort into sustaining and
purifying the this view that he has but
what he cannot do is whatever he engages
in here he cannot spill outside with the
assumptions the external self the over there that's
the external self the over there that's
inconceivable because even one has those
thoughts they're seen on the background
of the memory of this this is
and that's effortless exactly yeah
effort effort is on the level of
acting out of the habits pressures and
Passions including trying to get rid of them
including trying to get rid of them
directly through all sorts of practices
and so on that's yeah we make therefore
cannot do that but the viewing itself
requires no effort
yeah because it's not like a view that
you hold as in in the sense of any kind
of view about the world that you by the
way any of you is
effortless that's why they're so hard to
uproot because you don't even you don't
even see how you're doing it because in
a way you're not doing it directly yeah
so that's not what makes the difference
to whether it's effortless or not it's
what it's right whether it's
contradicting the actual I don't know uh
Order of Things arrangement of the
Aggregates the experience as a whole and
so on or not whether it's aligned with
it
and that's why Dharma is used in the
changes phenomena and as the knowledge
of the way out the Dharma yeah because
they're both still phenomenal it's
phenomena he's just rightly established right
he's just rightly established right
order of phenomenon and wrong order for
another there is no third option
there is no third option
so if the right order of phenomena is
established with this this is
this passion will have to be an
inevitable result you know as the what
was that the similar gives like as the
the mountains kind of the river slopes
down the mountain it goes into that
direction has to go that way because
that's where the mountain slopes
so if you know if your scope is upon the
establish upon the right order the the
mind will have to slope towards nibana
towards this passion until it's cooling
down to its removal of ownership and any
traces of
basically so when the ownership of a lot
of that phenomena we start describing
that the biggest sense itself the fact
the moment you start seeing it as an
ambiguous phenomena that endures the
peripheral in either here or there but
know that it's between the two yeah
that's only the beginning of of uh
relinquishing it relinquishing the
ownership of it
and that's why I keep saying the past
talks you don't remove the Atta like all
that phenomenon is gone no you remove
the ownership of it thus akka becomes
but the thing is there
the creature the individual whatever you
want to call it it's still there
that ambigued ambiguous sense of self of
these five Aggregates of these memories
in future plan and everything else it
remains there is just not thoroughly not
well thoroughly uh impossible to own
many other directions to go to
the questions
um
so I am
have often thought about these two
directions in terms of I mean it's
important to clarify that it's Direction
in a sense that you never access them
they're they're only right and even if
you're like not necessarily
thinking about either of them you
realize you are within them yeah you're
non-thinking you're ignoring your
distraction is within the this and this
is within what's presently attended to
even in unawareness and the memory of it
while it's presently unattended to even
in unawareness and there's a so there's
there's always simultaneously six of
these what you're attending to in Sixth
Sense well yeah but we don't need to
complicated what do you think about
what do you think about
um
instead of defining in relation the
direction of what you're attending to in
the direction of where attention is
coming from how I mean
um that that
um yeah yeah exactly that's what the
only two is the warmth of what you're
looking at yeah that's simultaneously
present as what this is right so what
you're looking at this experience what
you're touching feelings and sensating
and so on it's there with that image is
it's not in you in me is there with that
image yeah so it's just outside and more
outside so to speak internally speaking
and accessible yeah inaccessible
that's what the um what was it the
description of an arrowhead
one who is completely developed and
fulfilled and abandoned everything to be
abandoned in account of seeing this and
this is it says for him all that's left
is this um
this uh
body this conscious Body by this this
thing and all the name and form externally so
and all the name and form externally so
it's just the more you practice these
two internal points of view attention
and memory attention memory attention
memory attention memory simultaneous
present the more extent all the whole thing is
the more extent all the whole thing is
becoming
they'll become two external points of
view and thus there's nothing in me
that's already external to my own sense
of self my sense of self external to
itself that's not mine
that's why it's something it's a bit
ambiguous in the suitors as well between
that usage of internal and externals
sometimes internal basically stands
unanimously as mine because that's where
mine is yeah but yeah so you will start
internally stop assuming the external
world and in the end that internal
non-assumption of the external world and
purification from atavada is seen as a
thing out there
that's like the body there to the extent
necessary the phenomenon the image of
the body the memory of the body there
understood as body there
to the extent necessary for the final
knowledge for the final uprooting of
passion so like practically speaking again
so like practically speaking again
nothing mystical about it
as I said you can have a memory of
something from 10 years ago 10 days ago
or you can have a memory of what you're
doing right now the image of it is the
memory of it simultaneously present
enduring giving the context to what
you're attended
yeah but stop putting yourself first as
the one who remembers start seeing
yourself as an enduring thing within
that memory and directly and and the
world is directly attended to
the the objects of the attention the
senses and that six senses already
the mind and the five senses
that's the experience as a whole with
this this is
and any notion of self ownership
Consciousness everything else between
feelings decisions past future plans
greed Joys it's all within this too
they are actually inaccessible there's
two sticks holding each other
and everything that's dear to me or not
dear to me is just
sitting there on top of it gratuitously
I cannot be mine
so practice of Sati basically is
practice of memory of your present body
posture memory not direct attention
so have a memory of your body push I
have a memory of your presently enduring
feeling I remember even present enduring
I remember even present enduring
thoughts again memory of it so emphasize
the memory point of view not directly
attending point of view that's how that
well that's what signs of the mind will
become apparent but that's how the whole
the shape of the ambiguous state of mind
or feeling and a sense of self that's
how it's going to be discerned that
memory is uprooting after in the sense
of yeah no matter what
it's resetting the right order I am yeah
I have to be in a body posture I have to
be breathing yeah yeah exactly yeah so
that's important and then when you have
inevitably thought that sort of took
away from the principle of this this is
you don't negate it try to get rid of it
stop thinking Focus no no you just have
a memory of it having it right here
right now and it's there and you realize
you do that long enough the knowledge
that it cannot it's inconceivable for me
to for it to be outside of this this is
will become established and there is no
going back from there
that's why the results in knowledge
even if you stop them recollecting the
two views sotapana's knowledge cannot be
undone that it cannot be outside
so I can ignore it because I'm too
occupied whatever
with the world with the family or
something to go back to lay life and so
on it doesn't matter when I stop and
think about it the knowledge that it
cannot be outside so the entire domain
the gratuitous Assumption of you know
Atta uh living there independent owner
and then the entire massive suffering
they're dependent on their deeply rooted
perversion is gone so that's why there is no second
is gone so that's why there is no second
Arrow hitting anaria savaka as the suit
to described because there is no that
far far deeply perverted older they
projected you out there even worse
um circumstances than you already are in
like yeah craving is bad conceit is bad
but not as bad as that
not as bad as that level of perversion
and and ignorance of this disease so see
the more you pervert it the more you own
it
which means the heavier it is which
means losing it it's going to be far
worse somebody with traces of conceit if
they were to lose their life health and
so on things that are dear to them won't
suffer as you would have said you will
have as a certain partner you will have
seven grains of sand the suffering left
in comparison to the mountain Himalayas
that you would have destroyed by getting
the right View and ceasing to assume
outside himself because you know the
Escape well yeah and factually because
the burden to Great degree has been made
inconceivable but that's why also like the right View
but that's why also like the right View
surpasses like understanding atavada
freeing yourself from
surpasses all the other bananas that
even without a rather you're not
necessarily automatically free but
they're all included within it because
on the level with this this is
view of silver assumptions isn't uh it's
Assumption of sensuality isn't and all
the other views all the other views it's
all within this with this this is which
is the fundamentally somebody who has
understood it is
but might not be free from
sensuality ill will and all the other
things that are in between
can we explore this discourse where the
Buddha talks to rahula about these five
elements and then he starts talking
first about Earth elements and then he
mentions like half the head half the
body skin teeth yeah
yes and and then he says
um you know that which is internally and
clung to or held as mine yeah and then
it says well but internal Earth element
and external Earth element both are the
Earth elements yeah can we say against
the backbone of our discussion that we
can also contemplate that Suitor by
saying you cannot just have internal
Earth elements you cannot just have
external Earth elements yeah basically
you need to have both for any of this to
be sure for all elements and even that
would also could stand for the principle
of this this is yeah that's exactly
that would be a valid approach sure to
show to that discourse and that's why it
is like on the level I see
it's not on the level of directly
attending and touching Earth and staring
at clay pots and so on as they did the
practice of casinos mistakenly like oh
you stared at that and that's how you
see it no it's recollecting the great
Earth have a memory of what you're
already in
solidity the the solidity sure solidity
you could even you could have it in
different factors but in this case he
was talking about Earth it'd be like
Earth so recall the properties of Earth
that's currently enduring Earth is not
elsewhere now while we talk about and
forget about it you are on earth
factually it's there endures as a base
for your experience
what are the properties of that external
Earth is like okay so can this internal Earth
is like okay so can this internal Earth
one that I'm paired with
partake in any properties that are
outside of the properties of Earth that are
of the properties of Earth that are
different to it they would not be
affected if the great Earth is affected
no inconsumable
stay that image with this this is and
with this is this is
that's it there will be no room for the
ownership to remain there clinging to
this part or that part or oh no way I'm
not this body but I'm the universe and
stuff like that which Universe the one
that changes against your will all the
time like forcefully violently disrupts
erupts this gets destroyed oh well
that's not you know because those were
the similar look at these gray mountains
they come to destruction they get
destroyed eventually what is to be said
about this tiny little
fickle Pebble in relation to the size of
this thing that's equally sort of just
unpredictable so with this this is yeah
yeah the properties
the properties of this cannot not be the
properties of this inferior thing and
that's the practice of casinos in the
nutshell the element of Earth fire and to the
the element of Earth fire and to the
point of the element of Consciousness
the most refined but the point for every
Casino they would have said and thus
would establish his mind on the level of
that great Earth
anything inferior to that cannot
perturbing so if you establish like
recollect have a memory of presently
enduring Earth while you're here on it
so to speak all the time think about
well what you're going to have is what
people have today when they worry about
what will happen to the Earth they're
going to get his anxiety and they call
it equal anxiety or something I heard
about it
because well even if it's not ecology
related you're going to have anxiety if
you're not relinquishing your sense of
self if you don't know what comes first
and what to look for because you realize
you are factually you're all of your
life's concerns Joys as I said
possessions Future Part all of that well
please supposes this enduring planet of
Earth this great lump of soil
to exist to be simultaneously present as
an uncontrollable unownable basis that
you are bound with
if something were to happen to that
Earth nothing nothing inferior
nothing nothing inferior
now if your mind is established on that
level I relinquish the ownership of
everything inferior and inferior change
to that cannot bother you but then the
Buddha says however those brahmins they
could factually establish the mind in
the right order on the right level to a
right extent
did not know the escape the danger the
gratification the danger and the escape
in regard to the element of that great
Earth in regard to the water fire air
Consciousness the target knows it
and that's why he's free in both regards
see those brahmanas outside of the
Buddhist dispensation who developed the
mind on the level of the Earth have to
some extent put it first
they did not see the dead Earth dead
Earth that you have the memory of well
you wouldn't have such a memory
knowledge recollection image if it
weren't for this here immediate Earth so
with this this is is what they couldn't
see kind of mystifying it in a way they
went too too much that side or too far
this side so they saw certain obviously
relationship of surmounting but they
didn't see that that great Earth is
defined as such on account of this
little body that touches smell tastes
oozes and so on that's it that's why the
entire universe is within this body that
is the measure of the universe and the
universe understand defined defines this
body so with this this is um
so but yeah if somebody who is still
concerned with this inferior
internal me my body sense of Earth
basically if you like what the Buddha
gave the advice to rahula if you
actually cultivate and apply to yourself
the properties of that great Earth
that's unbodied by these inferior
changes when people throw stuff on it
and dig it and destroy it it makes no
difference to it apply those same
properties to this internal because it
is the same thing it's the elements
um
it's your ownership they created they
get through this Division and mine